Barrels out of bond.
The day after the battle with the spiders, Bilbo and the dwarves made one
last desparing effort to find a way out before they died of hunger and thirst.
They got up and staggered on in the direction which eight out of the 13 of
them guessed to be the one in which the path lay, but they never found out if
they were right. Such day as there ever was in the forest was fading once more
into the blackness of night, when suddenly outsprang the light of many
torches all around them like hundreds of red stars. Out leaped wood elves with
their bows and spears and called the dwarves to halt. There was no thought of
a fight, even if the dwarves had not been in such a state that they were
actually glad to be captured. Their small knives, the only weapons they had,
would have been of no use against the arrows of the elves that could hit a
bird's eye in the dark. So they simply stopped dead and sat down and waited all
except Bilbo, who popped on his ring and slipped quickly to one side. That is why
when the elves bound the dwarves in a long line, one behind the other, and
counted them, they never found or counted the hobbit. Nor did they hear or
feel him trotting along well behind their torch light as they led off their
prisoners into the forest. Each dwarf was blindfold, but that did not make
much difference, for even Bilbo, with the use of his eyes, could not see where
they were going, and neither he nor the others knew where they had started from.
Anyway, Bilbo had all he could do to keep up with the torches, for the elves
were making the dwarves go as fast as ever they could, sick and weary as they
were. The king had ordered them to make haste.
Suddenly, the torches stopped, and the Hobbit had just time to catch them up
before they began to cross the bridge.
This was the bridge that led across the river to the king's doors. The water
flowed dark and swift and strong beneath, and at the far end were gates
before the mouth of a huge cave that ran into the side of a steep slope covered
with trees. There the great beaches came right down to the bank, till their feet
were in the stream. Across the bridge, the elves thrust their prisoners, but
Bilbo hesitated in the rear. He did not at all like the look of the cavern
mouth, and he only made up his mind not to desert his friends just in time to
scuttle over at the heels of the last elves before the great gates of the king
closed behind them with a clang them.
Inside the passages were lit with red torch light, and the elf guards sang as
they marched along the twisting, crossing, and echoing paths. These were
not like those of the goblin cities.
They were smaller, less deep underground and filled with a cleaner air. In a
great hall with pillars he out of the living stone sat the elven king on a
chair of carvin wood. On his head was a crown of berries and red leaves for the
autumn was come again. In the spring he wore a crown of woodland flowers. In his
hand he held a carvin staff of oak. the elven king's gate. The prisoners were
brought before him, and though he looked grimly at them, he told his men to
unbind them, for they were ragged and weary. Besides, they need no ropes in
here, said he. There is no escape from my magic doors for those who are once
brought inside. Long and searchingly he questioned the dwarves about their
doings, and where they were going to, and where they were coming from. But he
got little more news out of them than out of Thoren. They were sirly and angry
and did not even pretend to be polite.
"What have we done, O king?" said Balon, who was the eldest left. "Is it a crime
to be lost in the forest, to be hungry and thirsty, to be trapped by spiders?
Are the spiders your tame beasts or your pets if killing them makes you angry?"
Such a question, of course, made the king angrier than ever, and he answered,
"It is a crime to wander in my realm without leave. Do you forget that you
are in my kingdom, using the road that my people made? Did you not three times
pursue and trouble my people in the forest and rouse the spiders with your
riot and clamor? After all the disturbance you have made, I have a
right to know what brings you here. and if you will not tell me now, I will keep
you all in prison until you have learned sense and manners."
Then he ordered the dwarves each to be put in a separate cell and to be given
food and drink, but not to be allowed to pass the doors of their little prisons
until one at least of them was willing to tell him all he wanted to know. But
he did not tell them that Thoren was also a prisoner with him. It was Bilbo
who found that out. Poor Mister Baggins.
It was a weary long time that he lived in that place all alone and always in
hiding, never daring to take off his ring, hardly daring to sleep, even
tucked away in the darkest and remotest corners he could find. For something to
do, he took to wandering about the elven king's palace. Magic shut the gates, but
he could sometimes get out if he was quick. companies of the wood elves,
sometimes with the king at their head, would from time to time ride out to hunt
or to other business in the woods and in the lands to the east. Then, if Bilbo
was very nimble, he could slip out just behind them, though it was a dangerous
thing to do. More than once he was nearly caught in the doors, as they
clashed together when the last elf passed. Yet he did not dare to march
among them because of his shadow, altogether thin and wobbly as it was in
torch light, or for fear of being bumped into and discovered. And when he did go
out, which was not very often, he did no good. He did not wish to desert the
dwarves, and indeed he did not know where in the world to go without them.
He could not keep up with the hunting elves all the time they were out. So he
never discovered the ways out of the wood and was left to wander miserably in
the forest, terrified of losing himself until a chance came of returning. He was
hungry too outside, for he was no hunter. But inside the caves he could
pick up a living of some sort by stealing food from store or table when
no one was at hand. I am like a burglar that can't get away, but must go on
miserably burgling the same house day after day, he thought. This is the
dreiest and dullst part of all this wretched, tiresome, uncomfortable
adventure. I wish I was back in my hobbit hole by my own warm fireside with
the lamp shining. He often wished too that he could get a message for help
sent to the wizard, but that of course was quite impossible, and he soon
realized that if anything was to be done, it would have to be done by Mr.
Baggins, alone and unaded. Eventually, after a week or two of this snaking sort
of life, by watching and following the guards, and taking what chances he
could, he managed to find out where each dwarf was kept. He found all their 12
cells in different parts of the palace, and after a time he got to know his way
about very well. What was his surprise one day to overhear some of the guards
talking and to learn that there was another dwarf in prison too, in a
specially deep, dark place. He guessed at once, of course, that that was
Thoren, and after a while he found that his guess was right. At last, after many
difficulties, he managed to find the place when no one was about, and to have
a word with the chief of the dwarves.
Thoren was too wretched to be angry any longer at his misfortunes, and was even
beginning to think of telling the king all about his treasure and his quest,
which shows how low-spirited he had become, when he heard Bilbo's little
voice at his keyhole. He could hardly believe his ears. Soon, however, he made
up his mind that he could not be mistaken, and he came to the door and
had a long whispered talk with the hobbit on the other side. So it was that
Bilbo was able to take secretly Thoren's message to each of the other imprisoned
dwarves, telling them that Thoren their chief was also in prison close at hand,
and that no one was to reveal their errand to the king. Not yet, nor before
Thoren gave the word. For Thoren had taken heart again, hearing how the
hobbit had rescued his companions from the spiders, and was determined once
more not to ransom himself with promises to the king of a share in the treasure,
until all hope of escaping in any other way, had disappeared, until, in fact,
the remarkable Mr. Invisible Baggins, of whom he began to have a very high
opinion indeed, had altogether failed to think of something clever. The other
dwarves quite agreed when they got the message. They all thought their own
shares in the treasure, which they quite regarded as theirs, in spite of their
plight, and the still unconquered dragon would suffer seriously if the wood elves
claimed part of it. And they all trusted Bilbo.
Just what Gandalf had said would happen.
You see, perhaps that was part of his reason for going off and leaving them. Bilbo,
however, did not feel nearly so hopeful as they did. He did not like being
depended on by everyone, and he wished he had the wizard at hand. But that was
no use. Probably all the dark distance of Murkwood lay between them. He sat and
thought and thought until his head nearly burst, but no bright idea would
come. One invisible ring was a very fine thing, but it was not much good among
14. But of course, as you have guessed, he did rescue his friends in the end,
and this is how it happened. One day, nosing and wandering about, Bilbo
discovered a very interesting thing. The great gates were not the only entrance
to the caves. A stream flowed under part of the lowest regions of the palace, and
joined the forest river someway further to the east, beyond the steep slope out
of which the main mouth opened. where this underground water course came forth
from the hillside there was a water gate. There the rocky roof came down
close to the surface of the stream and from it a poor cullis could be dropped
right to the bed of the river to prevent anyone coming in or out that way. But
the poor cullis was often open for a good deal of traffic went out and in by
the water gate. If anyone had come in that way, he would have found himself in
a dark, rough tunnel leading deep into the heart of the hill. But at one point,
where it passed under the caves, the roof had been cut away and covered with
great open trap doors. These opened upwards into the king's cellars. There
stood barrels and barrels and barrels, for the wood elves, and especially their
king, were very fond of wine, though no vines grew in those parts. The wine and
other goods were brought from far away, from their kins folk in the south, or
from the vineyards of men in distant lands.
Hiding behind one of the largest barrels, Bilbo discovered the trap doors
and their use, and lurking there, listening to the talk of the king's
servants, he learned how the wine and other goods came up the rivers or over
land to the long lake. It seemed a town of men still throve there, built out on
bridges far into the water as a protection against enemies of all sorts,
and especially against the dragon of the mountain. From Lake Town the barrels
were brought up the forest river. Often they were just tied together like big
rafts and pulled a road up the stream.
Sometimes they were loaded onto flat boats. When the barrels were empty, the
elves cast them through the trap doors, opened the water gate, and out the
barrels floated on the stream, bobbing along until they were carried by the
current to a place far down the river, where the bank jutted out near to the
very eastern edge of Murkwood. There they were collected and tied together
and floated back to Lake Town, which stood close to the point where the
forest river flowed into the long lake.
For some time Bilbo sat and thought about this Watergate, and wondered if it
could be used for the escape of his friends, and at last he had the
desperate beginnings of a plan. The evening meal had been taken to the
prisoners. The guards were trapping away down the passages, taking the torch
light with them, and leaving everything in darkness. Then Bilbo heard the
kings butler bidding the chief of the guards good night. Now come with me,
he said, and taste the new wine that has just come in. I shall be hard at work
tonight clearing the sellers of the empty wood, so let us have a drink first
to help the labor." "Very good," laughed the chief of the guards. "I'll taste
with you, and see if it is fit for the king's table. There is a feast tonight,
and it would not do to send up poor stuff." When he heard this, Bilbo was
all in a flutter, for he saw that luck was with him, and he had a chance at
once to try his desperate plan. He followed the two elves until they
entered a small cellar and sat down at a table on which two large flaggins were
set. Soon they began to drink and laugh merrily. Luck of an unusual kind was
with Bilbo, then. It must be potent wine to make a wood elf drowsy. But this
wine, it would seem, was the heady vintage of the great gardens of
Darwinian, not meant for his soldiers or his servants, but for the king's feasts
only, and for smaller bowls, not for the butler's great flaggens.
Very soon the chief guard nodded his head. Then he laid it on the table and
fell fast asleep. The butler went on talking and laughing to himself for a
while without seeming to notice. But soon his head too nodded to the table,
and he fell asleep and snored beside his friend. Then in crept the hobbit. Very
soon the chief guard had no keys, but Bilbo was trotting as fast as he could
along the passages towards the cells.
The great bunch seemed very heavy to his arms, and his heart was often in his
mouth, in spite of his ring, for he could not prevent the keys from making
every now and then a loud clink and clank, which put him all in a tremble.
First he unlocked Balon's door, and locked it again carefully as soon as the
dwarf was outside. Balon was most surprised, as you can imagine, but glad
as he was to get out of his weariesome little stone room, he wanted to stop and
ask questions, and know what Bilbo was going to do, and all about it. No time
now, said the hobbit. You just follow me. We must all keep together and not
risk getting separated. All of us must escape, or none, and this is our last
chance. If this is found out, goodness knows where the king will put you next
with chains on your hands and feet too, I expect. Don't argue. There's a good
fellow. Then off he went from door to door until his following had grown to
12. None of them many too nimble. What with the dark, and what with their long imprisonment?
Bilbo's heart thumped every time one of them bumped into another or grunted or
whispered in the dark.
Drat this dwarfish racket," he said to himself. But all went well, and they met
no guards. As a matter of fact, there was a great autumn feast in the woods
that night, and in the halls above.
Nearly all the king's folk were merrymaking.
At last, after much blundering, they came to Thoren's dungeon, far down in a
deep place, and fortunately not far from the sellers.
Upon my word, said Thorin, when Bilbo whispered to him to come out and join
his friends, Gandalf spoke true as usual. A pretty fine burglar you make,
it seems, when the time comes. I am sure we are all forever at your service,
whatever happens after this. But what comes next?"
Bilbo saw that the time had come to explain his idea as far as he could, but
he did not feel at all sure how the doors would take it. His fears were
quite justified, for they did not like it a bit, and started grumbling loudly
in spite of their danger. "We shall be bruised and battered to pieces and
drowned too for certain," they muttered.
"We thought you had got some sensible notion when you managed to get hold of
the keys. This is a mad idea."
Very well, said Bilbo, very downcast, and also rather annoyed. Come along back
to your nice cells, and I will lock you all in again, and you can sit there
comfortably and think of a better plan.
But I don't suppose I shall ever get hold of the keys again, even if I feel
inclined to try.
That was too much for them, and they calmed down. In the end, of course, they
had to do just what Bilbo suggested, because it was obviously impossible for
them to try and find their way into the upper holes, or to fight their way out
of gates that closed by magic, and it was no good grumbling in the passages
until they were caught again. So, following the hobbit, down into the
lowest cellars they crept, they passed a door through which the chief guard and
the butler could be seen still happily snoring with smiles upon their faces.
The wine of Darwinian brings deep and pleasant dreams. There would be a
different expression on the face of the chief guard next day, even though Bilbo,
before they went on, stole in and kindheartedly put the keys back on his
belt. "That will save him some of the trouble he is in for," said Mr. Baggins
to himself. "He wasn't a bad fellow, and quite decent to the prisoners. It will
puzzle them all, too. They will think we had a very strong magic to pass through
all those locked doors and disappear.
Disappear. We have got to get busy very quick if that is to happen. Balon was
told off to watch the guard and the butler and give warning if they stirred.
The rest went into the adjoining cellar with the trap doors. There was little
time to lose. Before long, as Bilbo knew, some elves were under orders to
come down and help the butler get the empty barrels through the doors into the
stream. These were in fact already standing in rows in the middle of the
floor waiting to be pushed off. Some of them were wine barrels, and these were
not much use, as they could not easily be opened at the end without a deal of
noise, nor could they easily be secured again. But among them were several
others which had been used for bringing other stuffs, butter, apples, and all
sorts of things to the king's palace.
They soon found 13 with room enough for a dwarf at each. In fact, some were too
roomy, and as they climbed in, the dwarves thought anxiously of the shaking
and the bumping they would get inside, though Bilbo did his best to find straw
and other stuff to pack them in, as cozily as could be managed in a short time.
At last 12 dwarves were stowed. Thoren had given a lot of trouble and turned
and twisted in his tub and grumbled like a large dog in a small kennel, while
Balon, who came last, made a great fuss about his air holes, and said he was
stifling even before his lid was on.
Bilbo had done what he could to close holes in the sides of the barrels, and
to fix on all the lids as safely as could be managed, and now he was left
alone again, running round putting the finishing touches to the packing, and
hoping against hope that his plan would come off. It had not been done a bit too
soon. Only a minute or two after Balam's lid had been fitted on, there came the
sound of voices and the flicker of lights. A number of elves came laughing
and talking into the cellars and singing snatches of song. They had left a merry
feast in one of the halls and were bent on returning as soon as they could.
Where's old Gallian the butler? said one. I haven't seen him at the tables
tonight. He ought to be here now to show
us what is to be done. I shall be angry if the old slow coach is late, said
another. I have no wish to waste time down here while the song is up. Haha!"
came a cry. "Here's the old villain with his head on a jug. He's been having a
little feast all to himself and his friend, the captain." "Shake him! Wake
him!" shouted the others impatiently.
"Gallion was not at all pleased at being shaken or wakened, and still less at
being laughed at. "You're all late," he grumbled. "Here am I waiting and waiting
down here, while you fellows drink and make merry and forget your tasks. Small
wonder if I fall asleep from weariness.
Small wonder, said they, when the explanation stands close at hand in a
jug. Come give us a taste of your sleeping drought before we fall to. No
need to wake the turnkey yonder. He has had his share by the looks of it. Then
they drank once round and became mighty merry all of a sudden, but they did not
quite lose their wits. Save us, Gallion, cried some. You began your feasting
early and muddled your wits. You have stacked some full casks here instead of
the empty ones, if there is anything in weight. Get on with the work, grow the
butler. There is nothing in the feeling of weight in an idle toss pot's arms.
These are the ones to go and no others.
Do as I say.
Very well, very well, they answered, rolling the barrels to the opening. on
your head be it if the king's full butter tubs and his best wine is pushed
into the river for the lakemen to feast on for nothing. Roll, roll, roll, roll,
roll, rolling down the hole. Heave ho, splash, plump. Down they go, down they
bump. So they sang as first one barrel and then another rumbled to the dark
opening and was pushed over into the cold water some feet below. Some were
barrels really empty, some were tubs neatly packed with a door featur. But
down they all went, one after another, with many a clash and a bump, thudding
on top of ones below, smacking into the water, jostling against the walls of the
tunnel, knocking into one another, and bobbing away down the current. It was
just at this moment that Bilbo suddenly discovered the weak point in his plan.
Most likely you saw it some time ago and have been laughing at him, but I don't
suppose you would have done half as well yourselves in his place. Of course, he
was not in a barrel himself, nor was there anyone to pack him in, even if
there had been a chance. It looked as if he would certainly lose his friends this
time. Nearly all of them had already disappeared through the dark trap door,
and get utterly left behind, and have to stay lurking as a permanent burglar in
the elf caves forever. For even if he could have escaped through the upper
gates at once, he had precious small chance of ever finding the doors again.
He did not know the way by land to the place where the barrels were collected.
He wondered what on earth would happen to them without him, for he had not had
time to tell the dwarves all that he had learned, or what he had meant to do once
they were out of the wood. While all these thoughts were passing through his
mind, the elves, being very merry, began to sing a song round the river door.
Some had already gone to haul on the ropes which pulled up the port colis at
the water gate, so as to let out the barrels as soon as they were all afloat
below. Down the swift, dark stream you go, back to lands you once did know.
Leave the holes and caverns deep. Leave the northern mountains steep where the
forest wide and dim stoops and shadow gray and grim. Float beyond the world of
trees out into the whispering breeze.
Past the rushes, past the reeds, past the marshes waving weeds, through the
mist that riseth white, up from mere and pool at night. Follow, follow stars that
leap up the heavens cold and steep. Turn when dawn comes over land, over rapid,
over sand, south away and south away.
Seek the sunlight and the day. Back to pasture, back to me, where the kind and
oxen feed, back to gardens on the hills, where the berry swells and fills under
sunlight, under day. South away, and south away, down the swift, dark stream
you go, back to lands you once did. Now the very last barrel was being rolled to
the doors. In despair and not knowing what else to do, poor little Bilbo
caught hold of it and was pushed over the edge with it. Down into the water he
fell, splash into the cold, dark water with the barrel on top of him. He came
up again, spluttering and clinging to the wood like a rat, but for all his
efforts he could not scramble on top.
Every time he tried, the barrel rolled round and ducked him under again.
It was really empty and floated light as a cork. Though his ears were full of
water, he could hear the elves still singing in the cellar above.
Then suddenly the trap doors fell to with a boom, and their voices faded
away. He was in the dark tunnel, floating in icy water, all alone, for
you cannot count friends that are all packed up in barrels.
Very soon a gray patch came in the darkness ahead. He heard the creek of
the watergate being hauled up, and he found that he was in the midst of a
bobbing and bumping mass of casks and tubs, all pressing together to pass
under the arch and get out into the open
stream. He had as much as he could do to prevent himself from being hustled and
battered to bits, but at last the jostling crowd began to break up and
swing off one by one under the stony arch and away. Then he saw that it would
have been no good even if he had managed to get a stride his barrel, for there
was no room to spare, not even for a hobbit, between its top and the suddenly
stooping roof where the gate was. Out they went under the overhanging branches
of the trees on either bank. Bilbo wondered what the dwarves were feeling,
and whether a lot of water was getting into their tubs. Some of those that
bobbed along by him in the gloom seemed pretty low in the water, and he guessed
that these had dwarves inside. "I do hope I put the lids on tight enough," he
thought, but before long he was worrying too much about himself to remember the
dwarves. He managed to keep his head above the water, but he was shivering
with the cold, and he wondered if he would die of it before the luck turned,
and how much longer he would be able to hang on, and whether he should risk the
chance of letting go and trying to swim to the bank. The luck turned all right
before long. The eddying current carried several barrels close ashore at one
point, and there for a while they stuck against some hidden route. Then Bilbo
took the opportunity of scrambling up the side of his barrel while it was held
steady against another. Up he crawled like a drowned rat, and lay on the top,
spread out to keep the balance as best he could. The breeze was cold, but
better than the water, and he hoped he would not suddenly roll off again when
they started off once more. Before long, the barrels broke free again, and turned
and twisted off down the stream and out into the main current. Then he found it
quite as difficult to stick on as he had feared, but he managed it somehow,
though it was miserably uncomfortable.
Luckily he was very light, and the barrel was a good big one, and being
rather leaky, had now shipped a small amount of water. All the same, it was
like trying to ride without bridal or stirrups, a roundbellied pony that was
always thinking of rolling on the grass.
In this way, at last Mr. wagons came to a place where the trees on either hand
grew thinner. He could see the paler sky between them. The dark river opened
suddenly wide, and there it was joined to the main water of the forest river,
flowing down in haste from the king's great doors. There was a dim sheet of
water, no longer overshadowed, and on its sliding surface there were dancing
and broken reflections of clouds and of stars. Then the hurrying water of the
forest river swept all the company of casks and tubs away to the north bank in
which it had eaten out a wide bay. This had a shingly shore under hanging banks
and was walled at the eastern end by a little jutting cape of hard rock. On the
shallow shore most of the barrels ran ground, though a few went on to bump
against the stony pier. There were people on the lookout on the banks. They
quickly pulled and pushed all the barrels together into the shallows, and
when they had counted them, they roped them together and left them till the
morning. Poor dwarves. Bilbo was not badly off now. He slipped from his
barrel and waited ashore, and then sneaked along to some huts that he could
see near the water's edge. He no longer thought twice about picking up a supper
uninvited, if he got the chance. He had been obliged to do it for so long, and
he knew now only too well what it was to be really hungry, not merely politely
interested in the dainties of a well-filled lauder. Also, he had caught
a glimpse of a fire through the trees, and that appealed to him with his
dripping and ragged clothes clinging to him cold and clammy. There is no need to
tell you much of his adventures that night, for now we are drawing near the
end of the eastward journey, and coming to the last and greatest adventure, so
we must hurry on." of course helped by his magic ring, he got on very well at
first, but he was given away in the end by his wet footsteps and the trail of
drippings that he left wherever he went or sat, and also he began to snivel, and
wherever he tried to hide, he was found out by the terrific explosions of his
suppressed sneezes. Very soon there was a fine commotion in the village by the
riverside, but Bilbo escaped into the woods carrying a loaf and a leather
bottle of wine and a pie that did not belong to him. The rest of the night he
had to pass wet as he was and far from a
fire, but the bottle helped him to do that, and he actually dozed a little on
some dry leaves, even though the year was getting late, and the air was
chilly. He woke again with a specially loud sneeze. It was already gray morning
and there was a merry racket down by the river. They were making up a raft of
barrels and the raft elves would soon be steering it off down the stream to Lake
Town. Bilbo sneezed again. He was no longer dripping, but he felt cold all
over. He scrambled down as fast as his stiff legs would take him, and managed
just in time to get onto the mass of casks without being noticed in the
general bustle. Luckily, there was no sun at the time to cast an awkward
shadow, and for a mercy he did not sneeze again for a good while. There was
a mighty pushing of poles. The elves that were standing in the shallow water
heaved and shoved. The barrels now all lashed together creaked and fredded.
"This is a heavy load," some grumbled.
"They float too deep. Some of these are never empty. If they had come ashore in
the daylight, we might have had a look inside, they said. No time now, cried
the raftmen. Shove off, and off they went at last, slowly at first, until
they had passed the point of rock where other elves stood to fend them off with
pulls, and then quicker and quicker as they caught the mainstream, and went
sailing away down towards the lake. They had escaped the dungeons of the king and
were through the wood, but whether alive or dead still remains to be seen.